听译、时间轴：刘巍然（学酥）
大家好 欢迎来到分布式系统的第6课
Hello, and welcome to lecture 6 on distributed systems.
今天 我们将学习共识
Today we will look at consensus,
这是分布式系统中
which is one of the most tricky,
最棘手、也是最重要的问题
but also one of the most important problems in distributed systems.
我们在上一节课讨论了状态机复制
And the context to this is, last lecture, we talked about state machine replication,
这是一种复制数据的好方法
which is a great way of replicating some data
可以将数据从一个节点/副本复制到另一个节点/副本
from one node to another, from one replica to another.
为了实现状态机复制
And in order to do state machine replication,
我们需要保证所有副本按照相同的顺序执行更新操作
we need to ensure that all of the replicas see the same updates in the same order,
我们可以用全序关系广播实现这一点
which we can do with total order broadcast.
这引出了一个问题 我们该如何实现全序关系广播
This now raises the question of how do we implement total order broadcast.
我们在前面介绍了一种实现方法
We saw one way of doing this is
由一个指定的节点来发送所有的消息 我们称此节点为主节点
to send all of the messages via a particular dedicated node that we call the leader.
此节点将排序所有消息
And this node is going to order all of the messages
保证所有节点都按照相同的顺序传递消息
and make sure that they get delivered in the same order on all of the nodes.
不幸的是 如果主节点崩溃
Unfortunately, if that leader crashes,
或者主节点因网络问题变得不可用
or it becomes unavailable due to a network problem,
或者主节点遇到硬件故障 或者主节点遇到任何导致错误的情况
or it has a hardware failure, or whatever anything goes wrong,
这种全序关系广播方法就无法继续工作了
then this approach to total order broadcast stops working.
现在的问题是
Now, the question is now really
如何解决主节点不可用的问题
how can we deal with the problem of a leader becoming unavailable.
一种选择是人工切换新的主节点
One option is to manually switch over to a new leader,
切换主节点这一过程称为故障切换
and this process is called failover.
人工的意思是 当主节点失效时 有位人工操作员会收到通知
So, manually means there's a human operator who gets notified if the leader fails,
这个人会选择一个新的节点作为新主节点
and this human is then going to choose a new node as the new leader.
这个人将重配置系统
And it's going to reconfigure the system,
让所有从节点都接受这个新的节点作为新主节点
so, change all of the followers to accepting this new node as their new leader,
同时告诉这个新节点 它已经成为主节点了
telling this new node that it now has to be the leader,
并赋予它实现全序关系广播的能力
and act in this capacity to implement total order broadcast.
如果你能提前知道主节点将会下线 那么这种方法就是可行的
And this works fine if you know in advance if the leader is going to go down,
确实有可能出现这种情况
which could happen,
例如 主节点因计划内的维护将会下线
for example, if the leader is going down due to planned maintenance.
如果你能提前知道
So, if you know in advance that
为了安装某个软件更新 你想在今晚重启主节点
you want to reboot the leader tonight in order to install some software updates,
那在安装软件更新之前
then you just move the leader role to a different node
你只需要把主节点角色赋予给另一个节点
before you install the software updates,
随后 你就可以在不出现任何问题的情况下平稳地取下主节点了
and then, you can take it down in peace and quiet, and no problems at all.
不幸的是 这种方法在有些情况下是不可行的
Unfortunately, this doesn't really help you in the case
例如主节点出现非预期内的崩溃
where the leader crashes unexpectedly,
或者如果主节点突然遇到硬件故障而停止工作
or if the leader suddenly develops a hardware fault and suddenly just stops working.
计算机有时候的确会出现这种情况 有时候确实会停止工作
And computers do that sometimes. They do sometimes just stop working.
有时 计算机可能会在最不方便的时间停止工作
In that case, it'll probably stop working at the most inconvenient time,
例如凌晨3点停止工作
so, like 3:00 in the morning.
此时 有些人就会接到一个电话
And so, somebody then has to get phoned,
他们得从床上爬起来 登录到计算机上
and they have to get out of bed and log into their computer,
为系统重新配置一个新的主节点
and reconfigure the system to use a new leader and so on.
这也是可行的
And so, this is possible,
一些数据库系统就是通过这种方式实现的复制
and some database systems do implement replication in this way.
但这就引出了一个问题：我们能否以某种方式自动交接主节点
But it does beg the question can we somehow do this leader transition automatically
这样我们就不用在凌晨3点把人叫起来了
so that we don't have to wake people up at 3:00 o'clock in the morning.
这种主节点交接方法正是共识算法要做的事情
And this transition to a new leader is exactly what consensus algorithms are all about.
共识和全序关系广播是两个不同的问题
So, consensus and total order broadcast are two different problems,
但他们实际上是密切相关的 我这就来解释一下
but they're actually quite closely related as I'll explain now.
在分布式系统中 传统的共识定义是
So, the traditional way in which consensus is formulated in distributed systems is that
你有多个节点 每个节点可以提出一个值
you've got multiple nodes, each node may propose a value,
你希望所有节点决定出一个相同的值
and you want all of the nodes to decide on the same value.
这就好像一些朋友要决定今天去哪里吃午饭
So, think of it as like several friends deciding where to go for lunch today,
朋友们推荐了不同的餐馆或购物中心
and like they propose different restaurants or shops to go to,
随后 朋友们应用某种处理方法选出了一个提议
and then, by some kind of process, one of those proposals is going to get picked,
所有人都会前往同一个购物中心或餐馆去就餐
and then, everybody is going to go to the same shop or restaurant for lunch.
这就是共识问题
And so, this is the consensus problem.
我们希望节点能够对提出的一个值达成一致
We want the nodes to agree on one of the values that was proposed.
你可以认为这个过程与全序关系广播是等价的
Now, you can think of this as being equivalent to total order broadcast,
因为在全序关系广播中
because in total order broadcast, what happens is
我们希望所有节点按照相同的顺序传递相同的消息
we want all of the nodes to deliver the same messages in the same order.
所有节点需要达成一致的是
And so, this agreement that the nodes need to come to
根据全序关系 下一个要传递的消息是什么
is the agreement on what is the next message to deliver in this total order.
你可以对需要传递的每条消息都执行一次共识
And so, you can keep doing consensus once for each message that needs to be delivered.
共识将保证所有节点将做出相同的决定
And the consensus will guarantee that all of the nodes will make the same decision.
在某一个时刻 一个节点决定好了特定的值
And so, at some point, a node decides on a certain value,
这相当于在全序关系广播中 此节点传递了这条消息
which means in total order broadcast terms, it delivers that message.
共识保证一旦决定好了特定的值
And consensus guarantees that once the value has been decided,
大家就不会再改变注意了
it's not going to change its mind about it.
在全序关系广播中 这意味着一旦传递了一条消息
And so, for total order broadcast, this means now once a message has been delivered,
那么这就是这一时刻根据全序关系应该传递的消息
it has been delivered at a certain point in this total order.
因此 共识问题和全序关系广播
And so, for this reason, the consensus problem and total order broadcast
在形式上是等价的
are actually formally equivalent to each other,
这意味着如果你得到了其中一个问题的算法
which means that if you have an algorithm for one,
你就可以将这个算法转换成另一个问题的算法 反过来也一样
then you can convert it into an algorithm for the other and vice versa.
经典的共识算法叫Paxos
Now, the classic consensus algorithm is called Paxos.
Paxos所做的实际上只是对单一值达成共识
And what Paxos does actually is only consensus on a single value.
但可以把Paxos扩展为Multi-Paxos
But there's an extension to Paxos called Multi-Paxos,
应用Multi-Paxos可以实现全域关系广播
which actually provides total order broadcasts.
Multi-Paxos可以对值序列达成一致
So, that provides agreement on the sequence of values,
因此可以用来决定消息的传递顺序
i.e., a sequence of messages to be delivered.
还有很多其他的共识算法
And there are a whole bunch of other consensus algorithms
包括Raft、视图戳复制（Viewstamped Replication）
including Raft, Viewstamped Replication,
以及Zab 即ZooKeeper原子广播（ZooKeeper atomic broadcast）
and ZooKeeper atomic broadcast, Zab.
可以用上述这些共识算法设计出开箱即用的全序关系广播
And they are actually designed to provide total order broadcast right out of the box.
在这节课中 我们将较为详细地介绍Raft
So, in this lecture, we're going to look at Raft in a more detailed way,
因为这可能是最容易理解的共识算法了
because that is perhaps the easiest to understand,
当然 所有这些共识算法都相当复杂、相当精妙
although all of these algorithms are rather complicated and rather subtle.
大家还记得 我们在第2节课讨论了不同的系统模型
Now, remember from lecture 2, we talked about different system models.
当我们讨论共识算法时 系统模型起到了非常重要的作用
And this becomes very important now when we are talking about consensus.
大家还记得 当我们讨论节点行为时
So, remember that when we were talking about node behavior, for example,
我们可以选择崩溃停止模型、崩溃恢复模型
we could choose between do we want crash-stop, or crash-recovery,
或者节点可以任意执行恶意行为的拜占庭模型
or Byzantine, in which case nodes can behave arbitrarily maliciously.
在网络模型方面 我们可以选择公平丢包链路
In terms of network, do we want to assume fair-loss, for example.
在同步时间方面 我们可以假设
And in terms of synchrony timing, are we going to assume
异步系统、部分同步系统、或同步系统
an asynchronous system, or a partially synchronous system, or a synchronous system.
Paxos、Raft、以及所有流行的共识算法
And what Paxos and Raft and all these popular consensus algorithms do is
都选择了部分同步、崩溃恢复系统模型
they choose a partially synchronous, crash-recovery system model.
你可能会问 为什么会选择这样的系统模型
And you might wonder like why particular these choices.
同步性是一个非常重要的问题
So, in particular, the question of synchrony is an important one,
因为我们说过 完全同步模型是不现实的
because we've said that a fully synchronous model is unrealistic,
因为实际系统总会出现网络延迟
because in real systems, you do get network delays,
不同时间点会出现不同的延迟情况
and you do get various delays that happen at various points.
当通过网络发送消息时
And so, we can't rely on
我们所设计的协议不能要求网络存在延迟上界
any upper bound of message latency when sending over the network.
我们能期望的最好结果是部分同步模型
So, the best we can hope for really is partially synchronous,
即大多数情况下 网络表现良好
where most of the time, the network is well behaved,
但偶尔也会出现消息长时延的情况
but occasionally, it has periods where messages are delayed for a long time,
或者出现节点在较长时间内暂停执行的情况
or nodes pause their execution for a long time.
理想情况下 我们甚至希望共识算法可以在异步系统中工作
Now, ideally, we would want consensus to even work in an asynchronous system,
这样我们就不需要设置任何时间假设了
where we make no timing assumptions at all.
但事实证明 这是不可能做到的
But it turns out that this is actually impossible.
有一个叫做FLP结果的不可能性证明 此结果证明了
So, there is an impossibility proof which is called the FLP result, which proves that
不可能在异步系统下实现一个共识算法
it is not possible to implement a consensus algorithm in an asynchronous system
且要求此算法总能够终止
in such a way that this algorithm will always terminate.
如果你有一个异步系统 即使你只假设存在崩溃停止节点
So, if you have an asynchronous system, and even if you only allow crash-stop failures,
甚至假设不存在任何复杂的节点故障情况
so, even not any of the more complex failures,
共识算法中总会因一部分执行过程
then there will always be some executions of the consensus algorithm
导致算法无法终止
in which the algorithm doesn't terminate.
如果你希望算法可以终止
And so, if you want termination, that is,
也就是说 如果你希望算法可以进行处理并总能做出最终决定
if you want the algorithm to make progress and eventually decide on something,
或者说你希望全序关系广播总能传递一条消息
or for total order broadcast to eventually deliver a message,
那么我们就必须设置时间假设
then we have to make these timing assumptions.
我们必须至少假设是部分同步系统模型
So, we have to assume at least partial synchrony,
这意味着我们需要设置超时时钟并处理超时情况
which means in effect that we use clocks for timeouts,
换句话说 我们有一个基于超时的失效检查器
or in other words, we have a timeout-based failure detector,
我们用这个失效检查器判断主节点是否失效
which we use in order to figure out if the leader has failed or not.
很重要的一点是
Now, importantly,
算法的正确性完全不依赖于时间
the correctness of the algorithm doesn't really depend on the timing at all.
即使系统的时间变得非常怪异
So, even if the timing in the system goes really bizarre,
共识算法也可以保证
consensus algorithm will still guarantee that
消息会按照相同的顺序传递
the same sequence of messages is delivered in the same order.
时间唯一会影响的是节点何时传递消息
The only thing that timing affects is when that delivery happens.
因此 如果你的系统会出现很多奇怪的延迟情况
And so, if you have a system in which there are lots of weird delays happening,
则消息传递会被延迟很长一段时间
then it could be that the delivery of the messages is delayed for some amount of time
直到系统自行解决了时延问题
until the system sorts itself out.
因此 时间确实会影响系统的活性 但不会影响系统的安全性
So, the timing does affect the liveness of the system here, but not the safety.
我们有可能
Now, it is also possible to
进一步弱化崩溃恢复系统假设
weaken the assumption about the crash-recovery system model.
我们有可能把假设弱化到拜占庭系统假设
And so, it is actually possible to go all the way down to a Byzantine system model,
我们假设一部分节点可以存在恶意行为
where we assume that some of the nodes may behave maliciously.
有可能为这类系统构造出共识协议
And it is possible to do consensus in that kind of system.
这类拜占庭容错共识协议
And these types of Byzantine fault-tolerant consensus algorithms
被应用在密码货币、区块链等相关领域
are used in the context of some cryptocurrencies and blockchains and that sort of area.
然而 这些拜占庭容错算法
However, these Byzantine fault-tolerant algorithms
要比崩溃恢复算法复杂得多
are rather more complex than the crash-recovery algorithms.
这些算法的效率也低得多
And they are also a lot less efficient.
出于本课程的目的
And so, for the purpose of this course,
我们将目光集中在Raft这个非拜占庭算法上
we're just going to concentrate on Raft, which is a non-Byzantine algorithm.
Raft只假设了崩溃恢复模型
So, it just assumes a crash-recovery model.
我们暂且不讨论拜占庭算法
And we will leave the Byzantine algorithms out of scope for now.
我前面提到过 共识算法的关键是选举出一个主节点
So, as we said, the key thing that we need of consensus is to elect a leader.
一旦我们有了主节点
And then, once we've got a leader,
此主节点就可以来决定消息的传递顺序
that leader can decide on the order in which the messages should be delivered.
我刚刚提到的所有共识算法
And all of the consensus algorithms I just mentioned
都会让主节点来决定消息的顺序
do actually use a leader in order to sequence the messages.
如何使用主节点、如何选举主节点
The details of how exactly they use the leader and how they elect a leader,
是算法与算法之间的差异点
they differ from algorithm to algorithm.
我将主要介绍Raft算法
So, I'll be focusing on what Raft does in particular.
我们会使用超时机制
And so, what we have is we use a timeout.
我们使用本地时钟来怀疑主节点是否已失效
We use local clocks in order to suspect whether a leader has failed or not.
如果你还记得
So, if you remember,
在部分同步系统中 失效检查器的检查结果
the failure detectors that we can have in a partially synchronous system
不一定总是准确的
are not always accurate.
可能我们认为一个主节点已经崩溃了
So, it could be that we think that a leader has crashed
但实际上 主节点工作正常 只是网络问题
when in fact, the lead is working just fine, but there's just a network problem
阻止我们与主节点进行通信
which is stopping us from communicating with the leader.
这就是为什么我说我们只能怀疑主节点崩溃了
So, that's why I say we can only have a suspected leader crash.
我们永远无法确定
We can never be actually certain
当超时发生时 主节点是不是真的失效了
if the timeout happened, that it was in fact a leader failure.
我们希望
And what we want is that
共识算法应该阻止系统同时存在两个主节点
the consensus algorithm should prevent having two leaders at the same time,
因为如果我们有两个主节点 它们可能会做出互相矛盾的决定
because if we have two leaders, they might make contradictory decisions,
此时 我们算法要保证的所有性质就都无法得到满足了
and then all of our algorithm’s guarantees are off.
系统出现两个不同的主节点
And this situation where you have two different leaders,
它们都相信自己是主节点
they both believe that they're the leader,
这种情况被称为脑裂
this is called split brain.
如果分布式系统发生了脑裂 这可是个非常糟糕的消息
And if this happens in a distributed system, it's usually really bad news,
因为这一般意味着一些数据将会遭到破坏
because it's probably going to mean that some data is going to get corrupted,
或者意味着你将丢失一些数据
or you're going to lose some data.
我们希望避免脑裂情况
And so, we want to avoid split brain.
必须谨慎设计共识算法
And the consensus algorithm has to be designed in a very careful way
使系统不出现脑裂情况
so that it doesn't suffer from split brain.
Raft使用任期这一概念来解决脑裂问题
And the way this works in Raft is that we have a concept of a term.
任期就是一个整数变量
So, a term is just an integer variable.
每次需要选举主节点时
And every time that there's a leader election,
主节点选举会发生在特定的任期中
that leader election takes place in a certain term.
每次我们启动一个新的主节点选举时 我们都需要递增任期
And every time we start a new leader election, we just increment the term.
Raft提供的主节点选举过程会保证
And the guarantee that the leader election provides in Raft is that
给定任期内 最多只能选举出一个主节点
there will be at most one leader elected in a given term.
主节点选举有可能出现失败情况 一届任期内没有选举出主节点
It could be that the leader election fails and that no leader is elected in a term.
但给定任期内 不可能选举出超过一个主节点
But there will never be more than one leader in a given term.
Raft确保满足这一性质的方法是
And the way this is ensured in Raft is that
Raft提出了一个规则：每个任期内 只允许一个节点投一票
we have a rule that in each term, a node is only allowed to vote once.
就像在议会选举那样 只允许你投一票
So, just like in a parliamentary election, you're only allowed to cast one vote.
这里也非常类似 假设我们有一个包含5个节点的系统
Very similar here, say, if we have a system of 5 nodes,
假设5个中的3个节点要选举出新的主节点
and, say, 3-out-of-5 elect a new leader,
A、B、C已经为新节点投票了
A, B, C have voted in favor of the new leader.
随后 如果C、D和E尝试在相同任期内选举出另一个主节点
Now, later, if C, D and E try to elect a different leader in the same term,
它们无法完成选举
they will not be able to,
因为C知道自己在这个特定的任期内已经投过票了
because C knows that C has already voted once in this particular term,
因此 C无法在相同任期内为另一个不同的候选人投票
and therefore, it will not vote again for a different candidate in the same term.
在新任期、新开始、选举新主节点时 每个节点又可以再次投票
In a new term, new start, new leader election, so, in that case, every node can vote again.
在共识算法中
And so, what we typically require in a consensus algorithm is that
每当我们想选举一个主节点时
every time we want to elect a leader,
我们需要quorum节点通过投票选举出该特定任期的主节点
we need a quorum of nodes to vote in favor of that leader in that particular term.
举例来说 假设我们有5个节点
And so, in this case, here if we have 5 nodes, for example,
我们要求有3个quorum节点 数量占到总节点数量的多半
then we could have a majority quorum of 3-out-of-5.
5个节点中的任意3个节点都有能力选举出新的主节点
So, any 3-out-of-5 nodes are able to elect a new leader,
这意味着系统可以容忍2个节点不可用
which means that the system can tolerate 2 nodes being unavailable,
此时 5个节点中的剩余3个节点
and the remaining 3 nodes out of 5
仍然可以继续前进 在必要时选举出新的主节点
can still make progress and still elect a new leader if necessary.
这是系统可以容错的基本思想
So, this is what gives us the fault tolerance.
每个任期只允许节点投一次票的方法
And so, this approach here of allowing a vote only once per term
保证给定任期内只能选举出唯一的一个主节点
ensures that within a given term, there is a unique leader.
然而 这实际上无法保证系统不会出现多个主节点
However, this does not actually guarantee that we will not have multiple leaders,
因为可能发生的一种情况是
because what could happen is that
不同任期内存在不同的主节点 但它们互相之间还不知道
there are different nodes that are leaders in different terms and they just don't realize it.
想象这样一个场景 我们有3个节点：节点1、节点2和节点3
So, imagine this scenario here, we've got 3 nodes, 1, 2, and 3,
假设节点1在任期t被选举成为主节点
and say that node 1 was elected to be the leader in term t.
但随后出现了网络问题
But then, a network problem happens,
节点1无法与节点2和节点3通信
and node 1 is no longer able to communicate with nodes 2 and 3.
节点1仍然活着 节点1仍然是主节点
Node 1 is still alive. Node 1 is still a leader.
但现在 节点2和节点3无法收到主节点发来的任何消息了
But now, node 2 and 3 don't hear anything from their leader anymore.
在某一时刻 节点2和节点3说
And so, at some point, node 2 and 3 are going to say
“好像我们的主节点不在了 我们需要在新任期内选举出一个新的主节点”
“Well, probably our leader is dead. So, we're going to elect a new leader in a new term.”
在任期t+1内 节点2和节点3将在它们之间选举出一个新的主节点
So, call a term t+1, node 2 and 3 are going to elect a new leader among themselves.
举例来说 节点2成为了新的主节点
Maybe node 2 is going to be the new leader, for example.
系统现在实际上出现了两个主节点
And now the system has actually got two leaders.
任期t的主节点是节点1
It's got node 1, which is the leader in term t,
任期t+1的主节点是节点2
and node 2, which is the leader in term t+1.
这看起来像是发生了脑裂 对吧？
And this looks like split brain, doesn't it?
我们有了两个主节点 这太糟糕了 我们不希望发生这样的情况
So, we've got two leaders. This is bad. We want to not be in the situation.
但不幸的是 因为出现了网络问题
But unfortunately, because the network is interrupted,
节点1无法通过任何方法知道
there is no way for node 1 to know that
它不再是主节点了 它已经被取代了
it is no longer the leader, that has been superseded,
因为涉及节点1的所有消息都无法被成功传输
because the communication simply isn't getting through.
因此 我们需要处理
And so, therefore, we need to actually deal with this possibility
系统在不同任期内同时出现不同主节点的这种可能性
there are different leaders existing in the system at the same time in different terms.
否则 这些主节点可能会在一段时间内做出互相矛盾的决定
And those leaders may for a little while make contradictory decisions.
然而 即使我们有多个主节点 我们也必须要保证
And we have to nevertheless ensure that we have total order broadcast
我们的全序关系广播不能违反其本该具有的性质
that we don't violate our properties even though we might have multiple leaders.
共识算法解决此问题的方法是
And the way that consensus algorithms do this is that
如果一个主节点决定传递一条特定的消息
if a leader wants to decide to deliver a certain message, for example,
主节点实际上不能自作主张
the leader cannot actually make that decision by itself,
主节点需要回过头来询问quorum节点
but the leader has to again go and ask a quorum of nodes
是否可以传递这条特定的消息
if they are OK to deliver a certain message.
协议通信流如下图所示
And so, what the communication flow looks like is something like this now.
左侧是主节点 右侧是两个从节点
Say, we have leader on the left and two followers.
首先 位于左侧的左节点被选举成为主节点
And so, first of all, the left node on the left needs to be elected the leader.
它会联系其他节点 并问道：“我可以成为新的主节点吗？”
And so, it's going to contact the others, say, “Are you OK for me to be your new leader?”
其它节点回复“可以”
And then, the others respond “OK”.
这意味着quorum节点投票选择出了新的主节点
Now, it's got a quorum of votes in favor of being a leader.
经过一轮选举 左侧节点成为了主节点
So now, the node on the left is the leader after one round of election.
现在 主节点想要传递一条消息
Now, the leader wants to deliver a message.
但我前面说过
But as I said,
主节点不能自作主张 直接传递这条消息
the leader cannot just make that decision by itself to simply deliver a message.
主节点必须再次联系从节点 并问道：
But instead, the leader has to go to the followers again and say,
“是否可以在任期t内把消息m作为下一个要传递的消息？”
“Are you OK to deliver message m in term t as the next message?”
从节点组成的quorum节点再次回复称：
And only if a quorum of followers again responds here and say,
“好的 可以在任期t传递消息m”
“OK, yes, we're OK with this message m in term t.”
只有当从节点没有听到其他主节点在任期t+1发出的消息时
And the followers will only respond positively
从节点才会给出正面回复
if they haven't heard of any other leader in term t+1.
现在 主节点再次得到了quorum节点的正面回复
So now, the leader again gets this quorum of positive responses.
现在 主节点可以放心地决定传递消息m
Now, the leader can safely make the decision to deliver m.
它可以告诉其他节点称：
And it can tell the other nodes that,
“好的 在我们的全序关系广播中 下一个要传递的消息是m”
“OK, m is now the next message to be delivered in our total order broadcast.”
这就是共识的基本原则 协议实际上包含两个投票阶段
So, this is the principle that we have effectively two phases of voting.
第一个阶段 由部分节点组成的quorum节点要投票选举出主节点
First of all, a node needs to get elected leader by a quorum of nodes.
第二个阶段
And then a second round happens
主节点检查是否可以决定下一个传递的消息
in which the leader checks if it's OK to decide on a certain message next.
我们提到的所有共识协议
And this is actually the underlying principle of
都满足这一基本原则
all of the consensus algorithms that we've seen.
我们将在下一小节详细介绍
And in the next section, we will look in detail
Raft实现这一系统的具体方法
at how Raft implements this particular system.